# Ata Kalirad, PhD

Postdoctoral research fellow Max-Planck-Institut für Entwicklungsbiologie Department for Integrative Evolutionary Biology Max-Planck-Ring 9 72076 Tübingen, Germany E-mail: <a href="mailto:ata.kalirad@tuebingen.mpg.de">ata.kalirad@tuebingen.mpg.de</a>
Web: <a href="mailto:https://kalirad.github.io/info.github.io/">https://kalirad.github.io/info.github.io/</a>.

#### Research

My current research revolves around understanding the causes of genetic incompatibilities using a computational model of RNA folding, theoretical exploration of the role of genetic robustness in evolution (both of which in collaboration with Ricardo B. R. Azevedo at University of Houston), and studying the importance of phenotypic plasticity in evolution using species form *Pristionchus* - a genus of nematodes - at Ralf Sommer's lab in Tübingen.

## **Current Positions**

2020 - Present Postdoctoral research Fellow, Max-Planck-Institut für Entwicklungsbiologie, Department

for Integrative Evolutionary Biology, Tübingen, Germany

2018 - Present Member of the Genetics & Biotechnology Committee at the Academy of Persian

Language and Literature, Tehran, Iran

## **Past Positions**

2019 - 2020	Postdoctoral research Fellow, Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM),
	Tehran, Iran
2017 - 2020	Member of the Scientific Committee for the Iranian Biology Olympiad (irBO) at the
	National Center for Development of Exceptional Talents, Tehran, Iran
2017 - 2018	Research Fellow, Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM)
2017 - 2018	Member of the Scientific Committee for the 29th International Biology Olympiad (IBO),
	Tehran, Iran

## **Education**

2011 - 2016	PhD, Department of Biology and Biochemistry, University of Houston, TX, USA
2008 - 2011	BSc, Department of Biology, University of Tehran, Iran

## **Publications**

#### **Peer-review Journals**

2020 H. Safdari, A. Kalirad, C. Picioreanu, R. Tusserkani, B. Goliaei, M. Sadeghi, Noise-driven cell

differentiation and the emergence of spatiotemporal patterns, PLOS ONE, doi: https://

doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0232060 (Co-first author)

S. Vafadar, K. Kavousi, H. Safdari, **A. Kalirad**, M. Sadeghi, *From indication to decision: A hierarchical approach to model the chemotactic behavior of Escherichia coli*, Journal of Theoretical Biology, doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110253">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110253</a>

2016

**A. Kalirad** and R. B. R. Azevedo, *Spiralling complexity: a test of the snowball effect in a computational model of RNA folding*, Genetics, doi: <a href="https://doi.org/">https://doi.org/</a> 10.1101/076232. 2017 (chosen by the editors as one of the May 2017 Highlights)

2011

H. Asgharian, E. Elahi, **A. Kalirad**, and H. Hosseinzadeh Saha, Sequence data on four genes suggest nominal Gerres lamentosus specimens from Nayband National Park in the Persian Gulf represent two distinct species, Iranian Journal Of Animal Biosystematics 6(2): 1-11.

## **Working Papers**

2021

James Lightfoot, Mohannad Dardiry, **Ata Kalirad**, Stefano Giaimo, Gabi Eberhard, Hanh Witte, Martin Wilecki, Christian Roedelsperger, Arne Traulsen, and Ralf Sommer, *Polyphenism and reproductive mode shape cannibalism behaviours in nematodes. (in review*)

2020

- H. Safdari, M. Sadeghi, and **A. Kalirad,** *Making ATP fast and slow: do yeasts play a mixed strategy to metabolise glucose?*, bioRxiv, doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/540757 (*in review*)
- S. Vafadar, M. Shahdoust, **A. Kalirad**, P. Zakeri, and Mehdi Sadeghi, *Competitive exclusion during co-infection as a strategy to prevent the spread of a virus: a computational perspective (in review*)

#### **Books**

2020

How to Tame a Fox (and Build a Dog), Lee Dugatkin & Lyudmila Trut, Translated into Farsi by Ata Kalirad, Fatemi Publication, Tehran (authorized translation - in press)

## **Presentations**

#### **Invited Talks**

2019 Darwin's revolutionary ideas, Origin of species: 160 years later, Institute for Research in

Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Tehran, Iran

2018 The fitness landscapes and the origin of species, 2nd Frontiers in Biological Sciences

Symposium, Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Tehran, Iran

2017 On the origin of species, 1st National Symposium on Evolution, University of Tehran, Tehran,

Iran

Making ATP fast and slow, University of Shiraz, Shiraz, Iran, May 2019 On the origin of species, 1st National Symposium on Evolution, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran

# Conferences, Workshops, and Meetings

2016 The melting snowball, Evolution Meeting 2016, Austin, TX, USA

2014 On the origin of species by means of Dobzhansky-Muller incompatibilities, Evolution Meeting

2014, Raleigh, N.C., USA.

A test of the snowball theory in RNA, 6th Annual Biology and Biochemistry Graduate Student

Symposium, University of Houston, 2014 (Recipient of the best talk award)

## Popular science talks

2018 A primer on evolutionary genetics, Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran (three talks

intended for undergraduate and graduate students with no background in biology)

2017 The role of scientific thinking in combating pseudoscience and anti-science, Seminar on the

Obstacles to Teaching Biology, The Academy of Sciences of the Islamic Republic of Iran,

Tehran, Iran

What evolution is not, 3rd Citalk Meeting (organized by National Research Institute for

Science Policy), Tehran, Iran

## **Teaching**

#### Courses

2019 Species and speciation, Graduate-level course, University of Tehran, School of Biology (Department

of Zoological Sciences), Spring 2019

General Biology 2, Undergraduate-level course, University of Tehran, School of Biology (Department

of Biotechnology), Spring 2019

2017 - 2020 Teaching various courses on evolution at the National Center for Development of Exceptional

Talents, Tehran, Iran

## **Skills**

Competent with scientific programming in *Python*. Familiar with *C*, *Mathmatica*, *R*, basic graphic design, and basic molecular/microbiological techniques.